A Guide to the William Faulkner Foundation Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #10677
William Faulkner Foundation Collection 1961-1973
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
10677
ca. 1000 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions on access to the Library's microfilms of the William Faulkner manuscripts in its custody; the microfilm may be consulted by any interested party, and it will be lent through the interlibrary loan system. Materials are constantly added. Long-term loans may be arranged. Use of the microfilm will be restricted to the premises of the borrowing library. No loans will be made to individuals. Researchers should enquire of the Manuscripts Division concerning availability of microfilm of manuscripts that are pertinent to their work. Most of the literary manuscripts in our collections written by Faulkner, both holograph and typescript, have also been published in facsimile in William Faulkner Manuscripts, 25 vols (New York: Garland, 1986-87).
By the terms of the agreement by which the William Faulkner Foundation transferred the original manuscripts to the University, access to the original manuscripts is restricted (to ensure the survival of the physically-delicate originals) to doctoral candidates at the dissertation stage of their programs, and to certain mature scholars and critics. But even these researchers must demonstrate need to see the originals that goes beyond the requirements of most routine research. A doctoral candidate at the dissertation stage, or other qualified researcher who believes that his or her work requires access to the originals must correspond with the Curator of Manuscripts prior to arrival at the Library to obtain permission for access.
No microfilm, electrostatic, or other types of copies may be made of materials written by William Faulkner that are in our William Faulkner Collections. Other materials in the collections may be copied subject to the normal rules of the Library established under the conditions of the Copyright Act. All copying is performed by the Printing Services Department of the University.
Acquisition Information
The records of the Ibero-American Novel Project were donated to the Library by Arnold Armand Del Greco of Charlottesville, Virginia, on December 30, 1985.
Scope and Content
The records of the Ibero-american Novel Project of the William Faulkner Foundation, 1961-1969 (1973), include ca. 1000 items of correspondence, certificates of merit, brochures listing award winners, announcements and statements regarding the project, printed items, and related material. Also present is a plaque awarded by the Foundation in 1964 for the most notable Ibero-American Novel, 1947-1962, to Ramon Diaz Sanchez for
Cumboto
.
During January through April 1961, William Faulkner visited Venezuela where he developed an interest in expanding his knowledge of the Spanish language. Upon his return to the United States, he set forth an idea concerning Latin American writers which involved the newly established William Faulkner Foundation. Faulkner, with the help of Linton Reynolds Massey and Arnold Armand Del Greco, made plans for a program in which three judges (under the age of twenty five) from each participating Latin American country would select an outstanding novel which had been published since World War II and that had not been translated into English. In assition, a grand award in the form of a plaque would be presented to one of the participants. The Foundation would then use its influence to have those novels that were nominated translated and published in the United States. The Ibero-American Novel Project evolved, and authors from fourteen countries were honored.
Award winners for 1962 were Eduardo Mallea, Argentina; Marcelo Quiroga Santa Cruz, Bolivia; Graciliano Ramos, Brazil; Jose Donoso, Chile; Carlos Luis Fallas Sibaja, Costa Rica; Marcio Veloz Magiolo, Domninican Republic; Miguel Angel Asturias, Guatemala; Enna Godoy, Mexico; Joaquin Beleno, Panama; Augusto Roa Bastos, Paraguary; Jose Maria Arguedas, Peru; Rene Marques, Puerto Rico; Juan Carlos Onetti, Uraguay; and Ramon Diaz Sanchez, Venezuela. Included is correspondence, in Spanish, between these novelists and Arnold Del Greco, a professor at the University of Virginia and director of the Ibero-American novel project.
Other correspondents include Jose Antonio Cordido-Freytes, Jorge Edwards, Donald Simon Klopfer( Random House), William A. Koshland( Alfred A. Knopf), Roy Land, Linton Reynolds Massey, Leigh B. Middleditch, Jr., Paul D. Summers, Jr., and Frank Harper Wardlaw, Jr., ( University of Texas). Del Greco also corresponded with many persons interested in the project, including interpreters and translators, editors, publishers, critics, professors, and American and foreign officials.
Organization
This collection in divided into two series: I. Correspondence, and, II. Topical. Folders were maintained in the original alphabetical order; modifications have been made to some folders.
Item Listing
- I. Correspondence
  - Correspondence: A-L, 1961-1964 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence: M-Z, 1961-1964 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Pending, 1961-1962 (Box Box 1)
  - C. A. Akin, 1961 (Box Box 1)
  - The Atlantic Monthly Press, 1963-1966 (Box Box 1)
  - Jose Maria Arguedas, 1962 (Box Box 1)
  - Fernando Bachelet, 1961 (Box Box 1)
  - Ruben Bareiro Saguier, 1961 (Box Box 1)
  - Idel Becker, 1961-1962 (Box Box 1)
  - Joaquin Beleno, 1963 (Box Box 1)
  - Ricardo Benavides Lillo, 1961-1962 (Box Box 1)
  - Raul Horacio Bottaro, 1963 (Box Box 1)
  - Roberto C. Bourbakis, 1961 (Box Box 1)
  - Tomas Luis Brause Berrata, 1961 (Box Box 1)
  - Margaret V. Campbell, 1963 (Box Box 1)
  - Ernesto Cardenal, 1961-1962 (Box Box 1)
  - Margarita Carrera de Wever, 1961-1962 (Box Box 1)
  - Jane Clapp, 1962-1963 (Box Box 1)
  - Jose Anotonio Cordido-Freytes, 1964 (Box Box 1)
  - Andres Cordova, 1961-1962 (Box Box 1)
  - Jose Luis Coto Conde, 1962 (Box Box 1)
  - Pablo Antonio Cuadra, 1961 (Box Box 1)
  - Ramon Rodolfo Cuello, 1961-1963 (Box Box 1)
  - Eliezer Curet Cuevas, 1961 (Box Box 1)
  - Carlos Esteban Deive, 1961-1962 (Box Box 1)
  - Nellt M. de la Cruz, 1961 (Box Box 1)
  - Ramon Diaz Sanchez, 1963-1970 (Box Box 1)
  - Jose Donoso, 1962-1965 (Box Box 1)
  - Guadalupe Duenas, 1961 (Box Box 1)
  - Paul DuFour, 1961 (Box Box 1)
  - Jorge Edwards, 1961-1962 (Box Box 1)
  - Roberto Esquenazi-Mayo, 1962 (Box Box 1)
  - Compania General Fabril Editora, 1962-1964 (Box Box 1)
  - Carlo Luis Fallas, 1963 (Box Box 1)
  - Juan A. Faria, Jr., 1961 (Box Box 1)
  - Miguel Angel Fernandez, 1961-1962 (Box Box 1)
  - Elizabeth Gaenslen, 1963 (Box Box 1)
  - Juan E. Gallagher, 1962-1963 (Box Box 1)
  - Luis Gallegos Valdes, 1962 (Box Box 1)
  - Ismael Garcia S., 1962-1963 (Box Box 1)
  - Adela Garcia Salaberry, 1963 (Box Box 1)
  - Roberto F. Giusti, 1961 (Box Box 1)
  - Emma Godoy, 1961-1968 (Box Box 1)
  - Cedomil Goic, 1961-1963 (Box Box 1)
  - Carlos Gutierrez, 1963 (Box Box 1)
  - Harper and Row, 1964 (Box Box 2)
  - Odette J. Hemenway, 1961 (Box Box 2)
  - Frederico Henriquez y Gratereaux, 1961-1963 (Box Box 2)
  - HOLIDAY, Arnold W. Ehrlich, Editor, 1961-1962 (Box Box 2)
  - Teodosio Imana Castro, 1961-1962 (Box Box 2)
  - INTER-AMERICAN COMMITTEE, 1963-1966 (Box Box 2)
  - Martha Jardi Abella, 1961-1962 (Box Box 2)
  - Alfonso Junco, 1961-1962 (Box Box 2)
  - Jus, S. A., 1961-1964 (Box Box 2)
  - Robert E. Kingsley, 1963 (Box Box 2)
  - Alfred E. Knopf, Inc., 1963-1964 (Box Box 2)
  - David Lagmanovich, 1961-1963 (Box Box 2)
  - Little, Brown and Co., 1963-1966 (Box Box 2)
  - Adelaida Lugo Suarez, 1961-1962 (Box Box 2)
  - Elliot McDowell, 1961 (Box Box 2)
  - Vincente Machado Valle, 1961-1962 (Box Box 2)
  - Eduardo Mallea, 1962-1963 (Box Box 2)
  - Rene Marques, 1963-1966 (Box Box 2)
  - Linton R. Massey, 1961-1973 (Box Box 2)
  - Juan J. Mathe, 1963 (Box Box 2)
  - Richard A. Mazzara, 1963 (Box Box 2)
  - Jose Ramon Medina, 1962 (Box Box 2)
  - Juan Mejia Baca, 1961 (Box Box 2)
  - Miguel Mejia Dutary, 1961-1962 (Box Box 2)
  - Celia Isable Mendoza, 1961 (Box Box 2)
  - Leigh B. Middleditch, 1961 (Box Box 2)
  - Rodolfo Mijango, 1961 (Box Box 2)
  - Miller, Florence J., 1968 (Box Box 2)
  - Misuraca, Sonia, 1967-1968 (Box Box 2)
  - Emilio Munoz-Marte, 1961 (Box Box 2)
  - Juan Carlos Onetti, 1963-1968 (Box Box 2)
  - Alfonso Orantes, 1962 (Box Box 2)
  - Alberto Ordonez Arguello, 1962 (Box Box 2)
  - Jose Miguel Oviedo, 1961-1962 (Box Box 2)
  - Isaias Pacheco Jimenez, 1961-1964 (Box Box 2)
  - Antonio Pages Larraya, 1961-1963 (Box Box 2)
  - Enrique Pezzoni, 1961 (Box Box 2)
  - Luis F. Prato, 1961 (Box Box 2)
  - Antonio Puerto, Jr., 1961-1962 (Box Box 2)
  - Marcelo Quiroga Santa Cruz, 1963-1964 (Box Box 2)
  - Graciliano Ramos, 1970 (Box Box 2)
  - Random House, Inc., 1962 (Box Box 2)
  - Augusto Roa Bastos, 1963 (Box Box 2)
  - Jose Roca Garcia, 1961-1962 (Box Box 2)
  - Sambrano Urdaneta, 1962 (Box Box 2)
  - Jose Ruben Sanabria, 1961-1963 (Box Box 2)
  - Santiago Rueda, 1961 (Box Box 2)
  - Simon and Schuster, Inc., 1961-1966 (Box Box 2)
  - Joseph Sommers, 1963-1964 (Box Box 2)
  - Armando Soriano Badani, 1961-1962 (Box Box 2)
  - Humberto Soto-Ricart, 1961 (Box Box 2)
  - Diane Stanley, 1964 (Box Box 2)
  - Department of State, U.S.A., 1963-1969 (Box Box 2)
  - Paul D. Summers, Jr., 1961-1963 (Box Box 2)
  - Hernando Tellez, 1962 (Box Box 2)
  - Baudilio Torres, 1962 (Box Box 2)
  - Ricardo Trigueros de Leon, 1962 (Box Box 2)
  - Antonio de Underraga, 1964 (Box Box 2)
  - University of Texas Press, 1964-1966 (Box Box 2)
  - Arturo Uslar Pietri, 1961-1962 (Box Box 2)
  - Marcio Veloz Maggiolo, 1961-1963 (Box Box 2)
  - Carlos Zipfel y Garcia, 1961-1963 (Box Box 2)
- II. Topical
  - Announcements and Statements regarding the William Faulkner Foundation, 1961-1964 (Box Box 3)
  - Author's Addresses, 1962 (Box Box 2)
  - Brochures: Ibero-American Novel Award, 1962 (Box Box 2)
  - Certificates of Merit: Ibero-American Novel Award, 1962 (Box Box 2)
  - Critiques on Ibero-American Novel Award Winners, 1963 (Box Box 2)
  - Expenditures of the William Faulkner Foundation, 1961-1970 (Box Box 2)
  - Judges and Sponsors of Judeges for the Ibero-American Novel Project, 1961-1963 (Box Box 2)
  - Models of Acknowledgement for Critics and Judges, 1962 (Box Box 2)
  - Models of Certificates of Merit Awarded to Winning Novelists, 1962 (Box Box 2)
  - Plaque Awarded to Ramon Diaz Sanchez for Most Notable Ibero-American Novel, 1964 (Box Box 2)
  - Printed Material regarding William Faulkner, 1961-1967 (Box Box 2)
  - Stationary for the William Faulkner Foundation (Box Box 2)
  - Summary of Ibero-American Novel Project, n. d. (Box Box 2)